Chevry Lomday Mishnayes Collection 0011.002.008c
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
Chevry Lomday Mishnayes
1918-1983
0011.002.008c
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
0.5 Cubic feet 1 Box
Appraisal note
This collection contains important information on the turning points and general nature of the congregation, but less information about activities.
Exhibition Placard
CONGREGATION CHEVRY LOMDAY MISHNAYES (“Society of Those Who Study the Mishnah”) SYNAGOGUE 148-150 Bedford Street Hartford 1924 or 1926/27 architect unknown The building concept of Congregation Chevry Lomday Mishnayes, another Orthodox synagogue, is totally different from that of the first three synagogues. The structure could easily be mistaken for a “Yellow Brick” apartment house were it not for the Star of David in the round front window. Budget constraints no doubt have dictated the modest character of the building’s design.
Biographical/Historical note
Congregation Chevry Lomday Mishnayes was founded in 1918 by a group of Eastern European and Russian immigrants under the name of "Chevre Mishnayos of Hartford" (roughly translated as Fellowship of the Mishnah).
For the first seven years the congregation had no permanent home. In 1925, the congregants built their first shul at 150 Bedford Street. In 1934, the synagogue re-incorporated under the name "Congregation Chevry Lomday Mishnayes" (roughly translated as Fellow Students of the Mishnah).
In response to the mass movement of the Jewish population to the northwest part of Hartford and to West Hartford, Chevry Lomday Mishnayes purchased the former Young Israel shul at 191 Westbourne Parkway in 1964. By 1983, attendance declined and the congregation merged with Teferes Israel.
Gershman, Charles; Greenberg, Maurice, Clothier, 1893-1965, Hartford, CT; Rosenberg, Solomon I., Rabbi; Zywica, Meyer F., Rabbi, Poland; Board of Directors; Chevry Lomday Mishnayes; Constitution, By-laws, Articles of formation; Synagogues; Synagogues -- Hartford; Teferes Israel
- Series I: Chevry Lomday Mishnayes Records & Manuscripts
  - Board of Directors/Activities, 1960-1968; Letters of correspondence; Cooper, Harry (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    This folder contains several original letters of correspondence from Chevry Lomday Mishnayes board directors concerning financial matters and other business matters related to the synagogue.
    Chevry Lomday Mishnayes. (Hartford, CT); Board of Directors; Synagogues -- Hartford
  - Board of Directors/Members, 1963-1967; Letters of correspondence, photocopy newspaper articles (Box 1)
    This folder contains original correspondence pertaining to the election of Isadore Gershman to the Chevry Lomday Mishnayes Board of Directors.
    Chevry Lomday Mishnayes. (Hartford, CT); Gershman, Isadore; Board of Directors; Synagogues -- Hartford
  - Buildings/150 Bedford Street, 1926, 1963; Original deed of purchase, letters of correspodence (Box 1)
    This folder contains the original purchasing agreement for the Chevry Lomday Mishnayes property on Bedford Street with member signatures, dated 1926. Also, 1963 letters of correspondence created by board director secretary Harry Cooper.
    Bass, Samuel; Chamansky, Joseph; Chevry Lomday Mishnayes. (Hartford, CT); Cooper, Harry; Dubowsky, Benjamin; Epstein, Louis; Forer, Samuel; Friedman, Philip; Deeds, Agreements, Leases; Synagogues -- Hartford
  - Buildings/191 Westbourne Parkway, 1964-1965; Original deed agreement, dedication programs, newspaper articles (Box 1)
    Chevry Lomday Mishnayes. (Hartford, CT); Gershman, Charles; Buildings, Hartford; Deeds, Agreements, Leases; Synagogues -- Hartford
  - Buildings/Locations under Consideration, 1956-1958; letters of correspondence (Box 1)
    This folder contains letters created by Harry Cooper to Hartford mayor.
    Chevry Lomday Mishnayes. (Hartford, CT); Cooper, Harry; Buildings, Hartford; Synagogues -- Hartford
  - Cemetery and Burial/Cemetery Administration
  - Cemetery and Burial/Cemetery Deeds of Congregation Members, 1950s & 1960s
  - Cemetery and Burial/Cemetery Invoices and Deeds -- Blank Copies
  - Cemetery and Burial/Purchase of Land, Garden Street, 1966
  - Constitution and By-Laws
  - Financial Information/Insurance
  - Financial Information/Tax Exemption Forms, 1960s
  - Fundraising and Donations
  - Historical Highlights
  - Incorporation Papers, 1918, 1934
  - Members and Membership, 1950s & 1960s
  - Merger with Teferes Israel
  - Miscellaneous
  - Music, Choir, Cantorial Programs/Weinberg, Hyman
    Weinberg, Hyman
  - Newsletters, 1950s to 1970s, 1950s-1970s
  - Rabbis/Zywica, Meyer F. (Box 1)
    Zywica, Meyer F., Rabbi, Poland
  - Ritual Matters and Shabbat Events (Box 1)